Welcome back to Am Northwest. You know,
if you love to collect books, how do you
know which ones are actually worth
something? Here to share his expert tips, we
welcome back antique appraiser Gary
Germer. Great Hey, good to see you. Good to
see you. >> Thank you for having me back.
You love to collect books, don't you?
>> books. I really do. That's one thing
people say you must collect everything
and I'm kind of a minimalist, but when
it comes to books, I have a lot. I like
books a lot. >> a minimalist. Really?
Okay, tell us more. >> things. I I thought
that you couldn't really collect
books because essentially they kind of
disintegrate. Well, that is a that is
a consideration. Age is not a friend of
books. So So, when people say they
have they're dealing with their mom's
collection, what do we do? I have 100
books. I ask two questions. One is were
these people book collectors
or were they book accumulators? Okay. So
usually a collector will have a subject
that they collect or an author
that they collect or a sales like
I have a collection here of
of Ray Bradbury, for example.
>> Is it we have a collection of that
had nothing but telescopes. He had
everything book there
ever was on telescopes.
>> And then um and so so people and people
can collect children's books in their
childhood. And so so when the collector
a collector will have a subject.
Accumulator is more like me. I'll read
and or a lot of you will read and put the
book on your shelf and and then over
a lifetime you've accumulated a lot of
books and rarely is there the most money
on those books are usually shake it out
of them, you know, that somebody's
hid the money. Okay. Oh.
The other thing is then what condition
are they in? >> Yeah. You got to think of
a book like a piece of glass. You know,
if you have a Tiffany vase and it has a
big crack down the middle of it, it's
not going to be worth much. Right. So you
have a you have a book an old book here.
The spine is faded. It's been sitting
on the shelf. And then this is very common
where it's broken right here. >> Oh,
yeah. The glue's coming undone. >> and
it's broken. So people say that well,
I'll ask what condition are they in? Well,
they're good for their age and I says
well, so am I, but that doesn't mean
I'm going to be walking the runways in
Milan anytime soon.
I didn't even let you finish that joke.
That was pretty good. All right. Yeah.
So So, one of the other things is is
like this collection of Ray Bradbury is a
good example. I have one right here.
Um I didn't know I when I saw this
collection, I didn't realize he made so
many books. He really wrote a lot. You
think Fahrenheit 4 4 51. Anyway. Here
it is. Yeah. 451. Got the number.
Yeah. Um but he wrote a lot of like
children's books. So when you're looking at
it, this is in good shape. The dust
jacket on a modern book can be at 80%
of the value. If you don't have the dust
jacket, it's going to kill the value.
The other thing about these is they're
all signed by him. >> Wow. So the guy
found and got him at saw the um went
and saw him and got signed at different
book signings and stuff. So that adds
a lot of value. First edition, signed,
just dust jacket. These others here are
just in pristine condition. They're not
that old. They're not that uncommon, but
because of those factors, it takes it
from being a $2 book from a garage sale
to being a $40 to $60 book. >> Got you.
Okay. And then um children's books, like
I said, and pop culture. People collect
their childhood. So like the Rolling
Stones, if you're part of the Rolling
Stones fan club. Yeah. These actually
sell for $30 a piece. And so if you've as
long as we still know who they are,
you know, and let's face it, uh Richard
Simmons is gone, but if Keith Richards
is still alive, so that tells you about
lifestyle. Um
people will collect it. I still have to
explain to younger people who Shirley
Temple was. So these things can fade
with time. >> Yeah, for sure. But people
collect their childhood. >> Okay.
Um the other thing they collect are
illustrations. So like this child's
this one here, the the little vixen is
illustrated by Maurice Sendak. >> Oh my
gosh. That's got to be worth something.
>> Maurice Sendak most people know for
Where the Wild Things Are. That's what we
as we grew up with. Right. You'll but
you'll find a lot of books that were
illustrated by him and somebody else
wrote the book. >> Okay. So that brings
this up to again, excellent. Everything's
excellent on it. It's a $200 book.
Oh, wow. Okay. >> Yeah. So then we go
back to condition. Here's some really old
books. People collect books like these
for their binding sometimes just cuz
they're old and leather and they look
great, you know, and but the it can affect
value. This book here that's on the stand
are is actually the Bible in pictures.
And it's by etchings that were done
in the late 1600s mid to late 1600s.
>> kidding me. Okay. But we don't
have the title page. It's been redone.
Somebody did it really badly with this
vellum that they kind of put on it.
>> I see. And so it affects but all of
the photo all all the photos all the the
etchings are in here. So if you can't
read, you can still study the Bible. Yeah.
Okay. Wow. So that goes from being a
$2,500 book to being a about a $500
book. Okay. But the thing is is that
if you get really old books like this,
they're going to hold their value such
as this one here. Um that's called The
Portland Girl at the Chafing Dish. It's
a cookbook. >> I love this. >> From the
18 from 1898.
Love this. >> Absolutely horrible um
recipes in it. I'm going to I'm going to
look at a couple recipes because I was
looking at this earlier. Uh Mussels a la
Portland. Yeah. Uh there was What
was a another good one here? Uh
Eggs with Macaroni. Yeah. There you go.
Uh Venison with Currant Jelly. There's
some of these are just really something
else. Yeah. They seem to have a big
thing about making in your chafing dish
a a a a white sauce with lots of butter
and then you dump the seafood in it. >>
Ship beef. Yeah. How can you How can you
do wrong? But see, that's a really really
rare book. It's a limited edition. So
that's going to have some serious money.
Okay. >> to also condition, we look at
these two here. We had these
rebound because they are um these
are the second edition of Little
Women, 1850s. >> Wow. And so
the binding had been breaking. So we did
a binding that was very similar to the
original binding >> Mhm. and the gilded
back. And so it brings it back up. Even
though it cost us $500 to have it done,
brought it up from being a few hundred
dollars now it's a $4,000 set. Wow.
Other things >> Wow. That's incredible.
>> Yeah. Okay. So other things to look
at are the bindings. Some people you
know, they decorate uh limited edition
small printing. This this book here that
it's in a case and it's just a limited
edition small press. You want to look for
those. Uh again, good
illustrator, limited edition.
Um Shakespeare, they made 800 million
copies of Shakespeare, but again, this is
a great decorator book. So a lot of people
buy these books and simply um display
them. >> display them and >> Yeah. and
talk about them. I love it. I love it.
Great Oh, some great information here.
Thank you very much. >> you want to
research it, ABEBooks
is where you want to go. Like Abe Lincoln.
Abebooks. There's others, but that's
a free site. Okay. And you can research
values. >> on our website. >> ABEBooks.
>> Gary Germer, thank you very much.